one that doesn't lose two-thirds of its power to waste heat, as is today the case in the US. We could use some more nuclear power, perhaps, although it would have to be an entirely different kind of nuclear power, because today's technology simply isn't cost-competitive with renewable energy whose costs are falling so rapidly. We'd need a new kind of plane, because I don't think it's particularly practical to ask the entire world to give up on air travel, especially as so much of the global South is, for the very first time, able to afford it. We need planes that won't produce carbon. We need a new kind of agriculture. Because we probably can't ask people to entirely give up on meat and go vegan, it would mean a new way of raising beef. Or perhaps an old way, since we already know that traditional pasturing practices can turn cattle farms from what are called carbon sources, which produce CO2, into carbon sinks, which absorb them. If you prefer a techno solution, maybe we can grow some of that mean in the lab. Probably, we could also feed some real cattle seaweed, because that cuts their methane emissions by as much as 95 or 99 percent. Probably, we'd have to do all of these things, because as with every aspect of this puzzle, the problem is simply too vast and complicated to solve in any single silver-bullet way. And no matter how many solutions we deploy, we probably won't be able to decarbonize in time. That's the terrifying math that we face. We won't be able to beat climate change, only live with it and limit it. And that means we'd probably need some amount of what are called negative emissions, which take carbon out of the atmosphere as well. Billions of new trees, maybe trillions of new trees. And whole plantations of carbon-capture machines. Perhaps an industry twice or four times the size of today's oil and gas business to undo the damage that was done by those businesses in past decades. We would need a new kind of infrastructure, poured by a different kind of cement, because today, if cement were a country, it would be the world's third biggest emitter. And China is pouring as much cement every three years as the US poured in the entire 20th century. We would need to build seawalls and levees to protect those people living on the coast, many of whom are too poor to build them today, which is why it must mean an end to a narrowly nationalistic geopolitics that allows us to define the suffering of those living elsewhere in the world as insignificant, when we even acknowledge it. This better future won't be easy. But the only obstacles are human ones. That may not be much of a comfort, if you know what I know about human brutality and indifference, but I promise you, it is better than the alternative. Science isn't stopping us from taking action, and neither is technology. We have the tools we need today to begin. Of course, we also have the tools we need to end global poverty, epidemic disease and the abuse of women as well. Which is why more than new tools, we need a new politics, a way of overcoming all those human obstacles -- our culture, our economics, our status quo bias, our disinterest in taking seriously anything that really scares us. Our shortsightedness. Our sense of self-interest. And the selfishness of the world's rich and powerful who have the least incentive to change anything. Now, they will suffer too, but not as much as those with the least, who have done the least to produce warming and have benefited the least from the processes that have brought us to this crisis point but will be burdened most in the decades ahead. A new politics would make the matter of managing that burden, where it falls and how heavily, the top priority of our time. No matter what we do, climate change will transform modern life. Some amount of warming is already baked in and is inevitable, which means probably some amount of additional suffering is, too. And even if we take dramatic action and avoid some of these truly terrifying worst-case scenarios, it would mean living on an entirely different planet. With a new politics, a new economics, a new relationship to technology and a new relationship to nature -- a whole new world. But a relatively livable one. Relatively prosperous. And green. Why not choose that one? Thank you. (Applause)
que no desperdicie dos tercios de su potencia en calor, como ocurre hoy en EE. UU. Podríamos utilizar un poco más de energía nuclear, quizás, aunque tendría que ser un tipo totalmente distinto de energía nuclear, porque la tecnología de hoy simplemente no es rentable con energías renovables cuyos costos están disminuyendo muy rápido. Necesitaríamos un nuevo tipo de avión, porque no creo que sea especialmente práctico pedir al mundo entero que renuncie a los viajes aéreos, sobre todo porque gran parte del Sur global es, por primera vez capaz de pagarlo. Necesitamos aviones que no produzcan carbono. Necesitamos un nuevo tipo de agricultura. Porque posiblemente no podemos pedir a la gente que renuncie a la carne y sea vegana. Supondría una nueva forma de criar carne de res o quizás una forma antigua, porque ya sabemos que las técnicas tradicionales de pastoreo pueden convertir las granjas de ganado de las que se conocen como fuentes de carbono, que producen CO2, en sumideros de carbono, que las absorben. Si Uds. prefieren un remedio tecnológico, quizá podríamos cultivar algo de eso en el laboratorio. Quizá también podríamos alimentar el ganado con algas, porque eso reduce sus emisiones de metano hasta en un 95 o 99 %. Probablemente tendríamos que hacer todo esto, porque como en todos los aspectos de este enigma, el problema simplemente es muy extenso y complicado para resolverlo de manera milagrosa. Y no importa cuántas soluciones implementemos, probablemente no podremos descarbonizar a tiempo. Esa es la matemática aterradora a la que nos enfrentamos. No podremos vencer el cambio climático, solo podremos vivir con él y limitarlo. Y eso significa que probablemente necesitaríamos una cierta cantidad de lo que se conoce como emisiones negativas, que también eliminan el carbono de la atmósfera. Miles de millones de nuevos árboles, quizá billones de nuevos árboles. Y plantaciones enteras de máquinas que atrapan carbono. Quizá una industria el doble o el cuádruple del tamaño del negocio actual de petróleo y gas para deshacer el daño provocado por esas empresas en las últimas décadas. Necesitaríamos un nuevo tipo de infraestructura, hecha sobre un tipo distinto de cemento, porque hoy, si el cemento fuese un país, sería el tercer mayor emisor del mundo. Y China está vertiendo tanto cemento cada tres años como EE. UU. vertió en todo el siglo XX. Debemos construir rompeolas y diques para proteger a esas personas que viven en la costa, muchas de las cuales son muy pobres para poder construirlos hoy, lo que significa poner un fin a una geopolítica estrechamente nacionalista que define el sufrimiento de aquellos que viven en otras partes del mundo como insignificante, incluso cuando lo reconocemos. Este mejor futuro no será sencillo. Sin embargo los únicos obstáculos son los humanos. Eso puede no ser un gran consuelo, si Uds. saben lo que yo sé sobre la brutalidad humana e indiferencia, pero les prometo, que es mejor que la alternativa. La ciencia no evita que tomemos medidas ni tampoco la tecnología. Tenemos las herramientas que necesitamos hoy para comenzar. Por supuesto, también las herramientas necesarias para acabar con la pobreza mundial, epidemias y también con el maltrato hacia las mujeres. Por eso, más que nuevas herramientas, necesitamos una nueva política, una forma de superar todos esos obstáculos humanos: nuestra cultura, economía, nuestro estado de las cosas parcial, nuestro desinterés en tomarnos en serio todo lo que realmente nos asusta. Nuestra miopía. Nuestro sentido de interés propio. Y el egoísmo de los ricos y poderosos del mundo que tienen el menor incentivo para cambiar cualquier cosa. Ahora, ellos también sufrirán, pero no tanto como los que menos tienen, que han hecho menos para producir calentamiento y se han beneficiado menos de los procesos que nos han llevado a este punto de crisis pero estarán más agobiados en las décadas venideras. Una nueva política convertiría el problema de gestionar esa carga, dónde cae y con qué dureza, en la máxima prioridad de nuestra época. No importa lo que hagamos, el cambio climático transformará la vida moderna. Cierta suma de calentamiento ya está lista y es inevitable, lo que supone probablemente cierta suma de sufrimiento adicional también. E incluso si tomamos medidas drásticas y evitamos algunas de estas situaciones peores, realmente terribles, esto supondría vivir en un planeta totalmente distinto. Con una nueva política, economía, una nueva relación con la tecnología y una nueva relación con la naturaleza. Todo un mundo nuevo. Pero relativamente habitable. Relativamente próspero. Y verde. ¿Por qué no elegir ese? Gracias. (Aplausos)